Guide to the Fred Eggan Papers 1870-1991
University of Chicago Library
Eggan, Fred. Papers
1870-1991(inclusive)
102.75 linear feet (196 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Fred Eggan (1906-1991) Anthropologist. Papers contain a wide variety of materials and media including correspondence, original manuscripts, teaching materials, field notes pertaining to Eggan's research among Native American groups and in the Philippines, microfilm, photographs, slides, and audio recordings. The papers date from 1870-1991 and cover all phases of Eggan's career as an anthropologist, documenting his earliest graduate and post-graduate field research, his work as teacher and administrator at the University of Chicago, his research and writing on native North American and Philippine cultures, and his extensive professional connections with many of the leading social scientists of the twentieth century.
Information on Use
Access
Photographs contained in Series III, Subseries 5, carry specific requirements for publication. For further information see series description. Series XI contains student evaluative material restricted until 2041. Series XII, Subseries 9 includes personnel and financial material restricted until 2039. The remainder of the collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Fred Eggan was born in Seattle, Washington on September 12, 1906. His parents, Alfred J. and Olive Smith Eggan, later relocated to Lake Forest, Illinois, a north suburb of Chicago.
In 1923 Eggan came to the University of Chicago as an undergraduate and continued on to earn an M.A. in psychology with a minor in anthropology in 1928. His master's thesis was entitled "An Experimental Study of Attitudes toward Race and Nationality." From 1928 to 1930 he taught psychology, sociology, and history at Wentworth Junior College and Military Academy in Missouri. During this interval he maintained his connection with the University of Chicago by working summers with Fay-Cooper Cole at Native American archaeological sites in Illinois.
In 1930 Eggan returned to the University of Chicago as a doctoral student in anthropology, completing his dissertation in 1933. Following post-doctoral field research in the Philippines he assumed an instructorship at the university, part-time for the Extension program and part-time for the Department of Anthropology. He was promoted to assistant professor in 1940 and associate professor in 1948. Not long after his promotion to associate professor he received a full professorship. He chaired the Department of Anthropology from 1948 to 1952 and again from 1961 to 1963. He was appointed the Harold H. Swift Distinguished Service Professor of Anthropology in 1963.
Eggan is credited with having achieved a synthesis between the British and American schools of anthropological study. The British school, as exemplified by Eggan's first mentor A. R. Radcliffe-Brown, was then dominated by the synchronic analysis of the function of cultural institutions. In contrast, American anthropologists, including Eggan's teachers Fay-Cooper Cole and Robert Redfield, focused on processes of diachronic culture change. Eggan united these two perspectives by attending to both structure and history using a method of analysis he called "controlled comparison." Based on results achieved by this method, Eggan's most important publication, Social Organization of the Western Pueblos, hypothesized that variations in the social structures of linguistically and culturally related Native American groups were the result of the varied historical circumstances experienced by each group. By applying this same method in his later work on the impact of modernity and Western culture on indigenous Philippine groups, Eggan formulated an inverse corollary: that differing social structures cause different linguistic and cultural groups to respond differently to the same historical circumstances. These insights concerning the interdependence of social structures and historical processes remain at the forefront of contemporary anthropological theory.
When Eggan enrolled as a graduate student in 1930, the Department of Anthropology had just become independent from the Department of Sociology, with Fay-Cooper Cole, Edward Sapir, and Robert Redfield as the core faculty. Sapir soon left the department and was replaced by A. R. Radcliffe-Brown in 1931. Eggan became Radcliffe-Brown's first research assistant in 1931-1932 and began research on kinship and social organization of northern Native American tribes. Under Radcliffe-Brown, Eggan completed a report on the southeast, plains and southwestern tribes.
Eggan continued field research on native North America in 1932 when he was awarded a Laboratory of Anthropology Field Training Fellowship to support his work on the Hopi Indian reservation in Arizona. There he met Don Talayesva, an informant with whom he developed a lifelong friendship. Eggan based his doctoral dissertation, which he completed in 1933, on research from this field work. Social Organization of the Western Pueblos, published in 1950 by the University of Chicago Press, represents a substantially revised version of this work. Eggan balanced his studies of the southwest with his later work on the Philippines, returning to the Southwest almost every year until he retired.
While waiting for final arrangements for a two-year post-doctoral fellowship in Australia, Eggan resumed field study among the Hopi at Oraibi and Second Mesa, Arizona. It was at this time, in the winter of 1933-1934, that Eggan began an association with John Collier and the Bureau of Indian Affairs. Collier invited Eggan to participate in a conference between the Bureau and the Navajo regarding sheep reduction and soil conservation. Later in his career, Eggan continued his involvement with the Bureau, serving as an expert witness in Southwestern Native American land claim cases.
Returning to Chicago in the spring of 1934, Eggan learned that funds he was slated to receive could no longer cover the cost of field research in Australia. As an alternative, he arranged to go to the Philippines. Fay-Cooper Cole had worked there under the auspices of the Field Museum in 1907-1908, and wanted Eggan to record changes in Tinguian culture since the time of his original research.
In the late 1930s Eggan developed his field material from North America and published on the Hopi, Cheyenne, Arapaho, and Choctaw. In 1941 he completed his first work on the Philippines, "Some Aspects of Cultural Change in the Northern Philippines." In 1938 he married Dorothy Way who was to become an anthropologist of the Hopi and Eggan's professional partner. A. R. Radcliffe-Brown left the University of Chicago for Oxford in 1937. In honor of his departure, Eggan edited Social Anthropology of North American Tribes.
In 1941-1942 Eggan's earlier acquaintance with John Collier led to participation in a pilot study on food and nutrition in the Southwest among Native American and Spanish-American communities. Graduate students conducted the research for this project under the direction of Eggan and Michael Pijoan, M.D. In October of 1942 Eggan was called to Washington to work for the Board of Economic Warfare. Three months later he was Chief of Research in the Office of Special Services for the Philippine government in exile. While carrying out research requested by President Quezon at the Library of Congress, Eggan again worked with Filipinos he had met on his first trip to the Philippines in the mid 1930s. After six months in this capacity, he attended the School for Military Government at Charlottesville, Virginia in preparation for setting up the Civil Affairs Training Program for the Far East at the University of Chicago. Eggan, as a Captain in the army, then returned to the University of Chicago to direct the Program from August 1943 to August 1945.
During and after World War II, Eggan's interests focused on the Philippines, although he still published on Native American subjects. Financed by a Fulbright grant, Fred and Dorothy Eggan spent the year 1949-1950 at the University of the Philippines. In 1953 Eggan won a Guggenheim Fellowship to further his work on the Sagada Igorots. That same year the Philippine Studies Program at the University of Chicago began operations. Eggan established the Philippine Studies Program with money from the Carnegie Corporation of New York, and directed the program until 1977.
In 1958-1959 Eggan was a fellow at the Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, Stanford, California. At the Center, among other projects, he prepared a report on the social and ceremonial organization of the Sagada Igorots.
After the early 1960s Eggan concentrated his efforts on teaching. In 1961 he participated in the first Peace Corps training program at Pennsylvania State University for the Bikol region and Bisayas in the Philippines. He was elected to the National Academy of Sciences in 1963. In 1965 his wife Dorothy died.
Four years later Eggan married his second wife, Joan Rosenfeld. In 1970 Eggan was a visiting fellow at All Souls College, Oxford. He retired from teaching at the University in 1974, but stayed on to manage the final projects of the Philippine Studies Program until 1977. He made his last visit to the Philippines in 1975. Late in 1986 he and his wife, Joan, moved to Santa Fe, New Mexico, where he continued work until his death in 1991.
Scope Note
The Eggan, Fred. Papers consist of professional and personal materials ranging in date from the 1920s to the 1990s. The collection has been arranged into eleven series. The majority of the collection documents Eggan's career as an anthropologist from his years as a graduate student in the 1920s and 1930s until his retirement from the Department of Anthropolgy at the University of Chicago in 1974. The papers provide materials from nearly all phases and aspects of Eggan's academic life. The physical and conceptual core of the collection is Eggan's ethnographic research as consolidated in his Native American and Philippine studies files.
The collection contains numerous types of material including original drafts and manuscripts, reprints, research and lecture notes, course and seminar work, correspondence, and field notes, as well as published and unpublished papers and articles by other scholars. Also present are non-print materials such as photographs, microfilm, sound and video recordings. A restricted series of letters of recommendation written by Eggan on behalf of others has been placed at the end of the collection. Authorship of papers, presentations, and lectures should be attributed to Eggan unless otherwise noted. All course numbers and titles refer to University of Chicago course offerings, and Eggan is assumed to be the course instructor unless other indication is provided.
The arrangement and structural composition of the papers attempt to follow, as nearly as possible, Eggan's own organizational strategies. These strategies tend to be subject or content based. The ethnographic series reflect a geographic ordering of societies which share certain environmental and cultural traits.
The arrangement of each series or subseries moves from the general to the specific within a given subject area. Correspondence, notes, and bibliographies are usually found at the beginning of the series. These are followed by manuscripts and drafts of Eggan's written work, and lectures, as well as course and seminar materials. These are succeeded by material pertaining to other authors, institutions, and related subject areas. Miscellaneous items such as clippings and reprint sets are found at the end of each series.
Series XII is addendum to the main body of the Eggan Papers. The series includes personal and professional materials ranging Eggan’s early academic life in the 1920’s until his death in 1991. It has been divided into 9 subseries. Subseries I contains personal and posthumous materials including memorabilia, calendars, notes and newspaper clippings, and condolence letters and newspaper clippings of Eggan’s obituary. Subseries II contains materials pertaining to Eggan’s activities as an educator, his association with a range of professional institutions and associations, and his role in many anthropological projects during his late career. Subseries III: Correspondence includes both personal and professional correspondence. Notable correspondents include E.E. Evans-Pritchard, Meyer Fortes, Claude Lévi-Strauss, Triloki Pandey and Charles Briggs. Subseries IV incorporates a chronologically organized catalogue of Fred Eggan’s published writings, with some additional drafts and proofs. Subseries V: General Files contains reprinted articles, papers and other writings, some annotated by Eggan. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by author’s last name, or in the case of an unlisted author, by title. Subseries VI: Dorothy Eggan Hopi Dream Research incorporates chronologically-ordered original and photocopied transcriptions of Hopi dreams collected by Dorothy Eggan between 1940 and 1957, and a paper based on her research. Subseries VII: Degrees, Awards and Honors contains the degrees, awards and honors achieved by Fred Eggan during his long career. It incorporates oversize certificates as well as artifacts. Subseries VIII: Photographs, Slides and Negatives incorporates photographic media pertaining primarily to Fred Eggan’s research in the Philippines. It includes oversize photographic prints taken by Eggan and others, including notable Filipino photographer Eduardo Masferré. It also contains glass lantern slides and emulsion negatives that may derive from Fay-Cooper Cole’s research in the Philippines and Indonesia. Subseries IX: Restricted includes personnel and financial materials that are restricted for fifty years.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Special Collections Research Center:
Browse finding aids by topic.
Eggan, Dorothy. Papers
University of Chicago, Department of Anthropology Records
Sol Tax Papers
Philippines Studies Program Records
Robert Redfield Papers
Ford Foundation Cultural Studies Papers
Subject Headings
Eggan, Fred, 1906-1991; Cole, Fay-Cooper, b. 1881; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881; Pehrson, Robert N. (Robert Niel); Radcliffe-Brown, A.R. (Alfred Reginald), 1881-1955; Redfield, Robert, 1897-1958; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939; Singer, Milton B.; Spiers, Leslie; Voth, H.R. (Henry R.), 1855-1931; American Anthropological Association; University of Chicago.Dept. of Anthropology; University of Chicago.Philippine Studies Program; Chaco Canyon (N.M.); Anthropologists; Anthropology -- Field work; Anthropology; Arapaho Indians; Bontoks (Philippine people); Cheyenne Indians; Choctaw Indians; Food habits -- North America; Hopi Indians; Ethnology -- North American; Ethnology -- Philippines; Filipinos -- Social life and customs; Gaddang (Philippine people); Ibaloi language; Ilokanos (Philippine people); Ilongot (Philippine people); Indians of North America; Isneg (Philippine people); Kalinga (Philippine people); Kankanay language; Navajo Indians; Sami (European people); Tasaday (Philippine people); Tewa Indians; Tigua Indians; Tinguian (Philippine people); Zuni Indians; Photographs
INVENTORY
- Series I: Biographical Materials
  This series holds items ranging in date from 1918 to 1990, and is divided into three subseries. Subseries 1: Personal Papers, contains notes on the Eggan family history, autobiographical notes, curricula vitae, appointment calendars, and transcripts of interviews and reminiscences. No family correspondence is included in this subseries. Subseries 2: Appointments, Awards, and Lectureships, preserves correspondence, certificates, speech and lecture notes, photographs, notices and newspaper clippings relating to fellowships, awards, and honors received by Eggan. Subseries 3: Assessments and Critiques of Eggan's work, provides critical essays and commentaries on Eggan's work by a number of students and colleagues, including Ernest L. Schusky, Raymond D. Fogelson, and Mario Zamora.
  - Subseries 1: Personal Papers
    - Autobiographical notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Biographical statement, curriculum vitae, bibliographies, 1964-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Biographical statement, clippings, pamphlet, 1949-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Family history, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Family history, Alfred J. Eggan, documents, diary entries, ca.1918-1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Interview, reminiscences, conducted by George Stocking, transcript, December 22, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Interview, "Fred Eggan Interview, University of Chicago, " conducted by Lawrence C. Kelly, sponsored by the National Science Foundation, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Appointment calendar, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Appointment calendar, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Appointment calendar, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Appointment calendar, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Appointment calendar, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Appointment calendar, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Appointment calendar, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Appointment calendar, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Appointment calendar, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Book reviews by Eggan, 1935-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Project lists, 1977-1979, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified, satirical manuscripts, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 2: Appointments, Awards, and Lectureships
    - American Anthropological Association, 1990 Awards for Excellence, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Bernice P. Bishop Museum, Honorary Consultant, correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - British Academy, Corresponding Fellow, correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, fellowship, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Guggenheim Fellowship, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Human Relations Area File, HRAF Fellow, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - National Academy of Sciences, certificates, 1961-1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - National Science Foundation, election, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Reed College, Bicentennial Lectures, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Royal Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - School of American Research, 1962, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - U.S. Army, School of Military Government, University of Virginia, The 4th Classbook, photographs, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - U.S. Army, Department of State, certificates, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - University of California, Santa Cruz, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - University of Chicago, annual faculty reports, research programs and proposals, 1940-1956 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - University of Chicago, annual faculty reports, 1965-1978 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - University of Chicago, Class of 1927, 50th reunion, speech, certificate, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - University of Chicago, "Comments on David Schneider's Retirement, " notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - University of Chicago, Convocation in Celebration of the Twenty-Fifth Anniversary of the Social Science Research Building, Fay-Cooper Cole honorary degree, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - University of Chicago, Harold H. Swift Distinguished Service Professor of Anthropology, correspondence, pamphlet, news releases, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - University of Chicago, Sigma Xi, memorandum, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - University of Chicago, Trustees' Dinner, speech, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - University of Illinois, Anthropology Club, lecture notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - University of Rochester, Lewis Henry Morgan Lectureship, 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research, Viking Fund Medal and Award, correspondence, clippings, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Wenner-Gren Foundation for Anthropological Research, Viking Fund Medal and Award, Award Committee, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 3: Assessments and Critiques of Eggan's Work
    - Festschrift for Fred Eggan, Alexander Spoehr, correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Festschrift for Fred Eggan, Jean-Claude Muller and Walter H. Sangree, "Irigwe and Rukuba Marriage, " manuscript, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Festschrift for Fred Eggan, Harold W. Scheffler, "Baniata Kin Classification, " manuscript, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Festschrift for Fred Eggan, Alexander Spoehr and Fred Eggan, "Introduction, " Contemporary Anthropology, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Reviews of Eggan's work, 1950s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Fogelson, Raymond D., "Fred Eggan, " manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Hatcher, Evelyn, "The Treatment of Kinship Change in the Work of Fred Eggan, " student paper, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Anthropological Fence-Straddler, " manuscript, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Read, Mary Eaton, "Controlled Comparison in the Work of Fred Eggan, " student paper, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Anthropologist Full Circle, " manuscript, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - A Comparison of the Theories of Eggan and Murdock, " student paper, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - His Contributions to Philippine Anthropology, " ca.1983 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series II: Correspondence
  This single series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent name. It combines much of Eggan's personal and professional correspondence, dated 1925-1991. Within the personal correspondence, once again there is a gap with respect to family correspondence. Eggan's professional correspondence documents his dialogue with many contemporary social scientists including Ruth Benedict, E. E. Evans-Pritchard, Raymond Firth, Meyer Fortes, Max Gluckman, Alfred L. Kroeber, Claude Lévi-Strauss, Sol Tax, and Leslie White. Significant portions of correspondence are also found in appropriate subject areas throughout the collection. In addition to correspondence with students and colleagues, much of Eggan's administrative work for various institutions and professional organizations, including the University of Chicago, is represented in the series. This material appears within the alphabetical sequence according to institution or organization name.
  - A, general, 1938-1990 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Aberle, David F., 1951-1987 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Academic Press, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Adams, Charles E., 1985 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Agogino, George, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Aikens, C. Melvin, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Aldine Publishing Company, 1965-1966, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Allen, Lafe F., 1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1963-1986 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - American Anthropological Association, 1962-1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - American Anthropological Association, meetings, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - American Anthropological Association, meetings, 1955-1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - American Anthropological Association, meetings, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - American Anthropological Association, meetings, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - American Anthropological Association, meetings, 1963, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - American Anthropological Association, meetings, 1975-1990 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - American Anthropological Association, committee meetings, 1950-1953 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - American Anthropological Association, Executive Board, minutes, 1961, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - American Anthropological Association, Executive Board, report, 1971, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1963-1976 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - American Ethnological Society, 1963-1984 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - American Ethnologist, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1962-1990 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - American Society for Ethnohistory, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 1)